# **GERARD CRICHLOW**

STRATEGY | CULTURE | CONTENT | COMMUNITY

## **PROFILE**

9 Warrington Gardens London, W9 2QB

+44 (0)7525823423

gcrichlow9@gmail.com

gerard270/culture-watch

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I'm a cultural stockbroker helping brands define their position in culture and in business. I've worked in global and regional roles across sport, fashion/retail, spirits, technology, and FMCG helping brands tell their stories.

Marketing for me is about people, culture and community geared towards driving brands forward with purpose.

I lead by example and am a firm believer in using creativity to move humanity to innovate, drive change and influence behaviour.

I am passionate about the power of creativity and design to improve people's lives and am committed to making art accessible to all.

I love sports, design and sneakers.

# **WORK**

Axe: DogeCan https://bit.lv/3PdsnHH Axe and Fortnite https://bit.lv/3vSxMx5 Axe: Fresh as Fr\*sh https://bit.lv/3JHqvZd Live Fearless https://bit.ly/3dOajIN Martini Smart Cube http://j.mp/31MZiue Honey Maid http://j.mp/1jjpMJN http://j.mp/2OKhNtw **Under Armour** http://j.mp/1jjoA9n #MorningWin http://j.mp/1fRwvGm Google Wallet

## **EXPERIENCE**

# **INTERPUBLIC GROUP (IPG)**

London

Global Strategy Director, AXE / LYNX

Dec 2020 - PRESENT

Lead global strategist for the Axe/Lynx brand across all IPG network partners.

- Led global repositioning of the Axe Effect to reframe masculinity for a new generation.
- Pioneered the 'Always There' social first model to brand building to identify subcultures in music, gaming and anime.
- Created an anime with <u>Lil Baby</u>, a new product with <u>Bzrp</u>, and a Fortnite map with <u>Bugha</u> that increased brand talkability by +400%.
- Collaborated with the global executive team to pioneer Unilever's first
  Talkability metric linking social media activations to brand power and sales.
- Delivered a 77% increase in shares globally -- a 10-year high for the brand.

#### **WORKINGVERSION LTD**

London

**Strategy Consultant** 

Mar 2020 - Dec 2020

Collaborated with start-up founders to define their vision, and scale through marketing.

- Led the renaming and brand positioning for CupClub, resulting in a new brand identity and new name -- ClubZero, and investment from Tesla, and JustEats.
- Worked with the founder of Amplify, to define their content and marketing strategy.
- Advised the founder of BlueBella to create a social first brand strategy to align with brand purpose and optimise social commerce.

**EXPOSURE** London

Freelance Strategy Director

New business pitches

Jan 2020 - Mar 2020

- Won £1m of new business from Nordstrom.
- Spearheaded editorial strategy for Berghaus' new line of lifestyle footwear, their Unlimited Repair program and Dean Street Collection.
- Transformed Brewdog's purpose strategy and launch plan, taking them from Rebels to Mavericks.

AMV BBDO London

Strategy Partner, Head of Cultural Strategy and Innovation

Oct 2014 - Oct 2019

Lead strategist for the Bacardi portfolio of brands in Europe.

- Developed cultural position, brand purpose and partnerships strategy for a portfolio of Bacardi brands.
- Reinvigorated creative briefs to celebrate subculture groups in key markets across Europe.
- Managed a team of strategists, coaching them to mind trends, develop inspiring briefs, and achieve their professional potential.

# **GERARD CRICHLOW**

STRATEGY I CULTURE I COMMUNITY

# **OUTSIDE INTERESTS**

#### COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

VICTORIA & ALBERT MUSEUM (V&A)

Advise the V&A's Audiences division on how to scale the brand globally and create a seamless V&A experience across all touchpoints.

#### THE SATURDAY CLUB

Masterclass instructor helping the next generation of creative problem solvers by exposing young people to creative industries.

#### THE YOUNG VIC THEATRE

Development Board Member, exposing the next-generation to the theatre experience.

# **OUTSIDE INTERESTS**

#### **INDUSTRY**

TEDX SPEAKER

'Is Human Contact a Luxury Good?'

LINKEDIN LEARNING INSTRUCTOR 'Designing Brands for Culture'

D&AD 2019

Jury Young Blood

CANNES LIONS 2018

Jury Social & Influencer

WARC Awards 2018

Jury Effective Social Strategy

DMA RUSSIA 2018

Keynote Speaker, Russia's largest marketing conference

# **EXPERIENCE** (Continued...)

#### **SPARKS & HONEY**

London

Director of Cultural Innovation & Intelligence

Oct 2014 – Aug 2016

Scale European operations and thought leadership.

- Addressed the stigma of women's periods in culture and directed The Live Fearless project reaching over 600+ million people, increased share of voice from 5% to 74%, and resulted in a Cannes Lion award.
- Led the European new business acquisition, resulting in wins from Mars, Bacardi, and Guinness.
- Directed a team of 3 strategists.

DROGA5 New York

**Director of Social Media Strategy** 

Feb 2013 - Oct 2014

Lead Droga5's social media practice.

- Spearheaded the creation of Droga5's social media strategy team and content production studio.
- Led the global Under Armour 'I Will What I Want' campaign featuring Misty Copeland and Giselle Bündchen.
- Managed the social rollout of Diet Coke's 'You're On' campaign, increasing purchase intent to +15.3%.
- Cultivated the social strategy for Honey Maid's "Love" video, which became one of the most shared videos in March 2014 with 350million+ views and won a Cannes Lion.

R/GA New York

Senior Social Media Strategist

Aug 2010 - Feb 2013

Social media strategy and playbook implementation.

- Oversaw the creation and implantation of Nike's first social media playbook to empower local markets to own their communities.
- Managed Nike Running's community to better connect, inspire, and enable runners through conversation and engagement.
- Led the global social media strategy launch for Google Wallet the world's first NFC enabled smartphone.
- Developed brand playbooks for Nike, MasterCard, Unilever and Walmart.

# **RUDER FINN**

New York

**Communications Strategist** 

July 2004 – Aug 2010

Research, polling and messaging for public relations.

- Employed a mix of qualitative and quantitative research for the messaging development for branding, web site copy, crisis communications, product launches, and press releases.
- Lead the creation and analysis of the "RF Intent Index" a study and interactive web site evaluating consumer intent on the internet and mobile devices.

# **EDUCATION**

### **GEORGETOWN UNIVERSITY**

Washington, DC

Page 2 of 2